Don Yoder Collection of Tape Recordings
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Don Yoder Collection of Tape Recordings 1951-1979
AFC 2003/051
Yoder, Don
3 boxes.
152 sound tape reels: analog; various sizes.
21 sound cassettes: analog.
1 sound disc: analog, 45 rpm.
2 photographs: black and white; 3 1/2 x 5 in.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center Library of Congress Washington, D.C. http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.home
Collection of field recordings made by professor Don Yoder to document various religious sects and religious and secular folk traditions primarily in Pennsylvania and in the northeastern United States. Included are recordings of Pennsylvania German conversation, interviews, hymns, prayers, church services including sermons, folk dance music, humorous songs, and folk festivals. Manuscripts include a few published articles by Don Yoder and various folk festival programs.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Yoder, Don, collector.
Organizations
Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival: (2nd: 1951: Kutztown, Pa.); Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic: (1st: 1961: Lancaster, Pa.); WEEU (Radio station: Reading, Pa.)
Subjects
African Americans--Social life and customs.; Baptists--Kentucky--Hymns.; Christmas music--Pennsylvania.; Field recordings--New Jersey.; Field recordings--Pennsylvania.; Folk dance music--Pennsylvania.; Folk festivals--Pennsylvania.; Folk music--Pennsylvania.; Folk songs, Pennsylvania German--Pennsylvania.; Healing--Religious aspects.; Hymns, English--Pennsylvania.; Hymns, German--Pennsylvania.; Italian American Catholics--New Jersey--Religion.; Italian American Catholics--New Jersey--Social life and customs.; Jews, Russian--United States--Social life and customs.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Music.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Religion.; Pennsylvania Dutch--Pennsylvania--Social life and customs.; Powwows (healers); Revival hymns--Pennsylvania.; Shakers--Religion.; Syrian Americans--Social life and customs.
Form/Genre
Field recordings.; Interviews.; Prayers.; Radio programs.
Administrative Information
Arrangement
Organized by format into the following series: I. Manuscripts; II. Sound Recordings; III. Graphic Materials.
Additional Guides
Partial logs for the sound recordings are available in the Folklife Reading Room, Library of Congress.
Acquisition
Don Yoder.
Related Material
Don Yoder Collection of Wire Recordings (AFC 1970/004).
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research; access restrictions for some recordings may apply. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Electronic Format
The sound recordings have been digitized.
Biograhical Notes
Born in 1921, in Altoona, Pennsylvania, Don Yoder grew up immersed in the traditions of Pennsylvania German culture. Educated at Franklin and Marshall College (A.B., 1942 and B.D., 1945), and at the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1947), Yoder was chair of the Department of Folklore and Folklife at the University of Pennsylvania from 1966-1969, and retired from teaching after 40 years. He authored and co-authored hundreds of publications, traveled and lectured widely, and held varied posts, including director of the Pennsylvania Folklife Society (which he co-founded), editor of Pennsylvania Folklife, president of the American Folklore Society, and Professor Emeritus of Folklife Studies, University of Pennsylvania. He is a member of Phi Beta Kappa, and has been elected fellow to the American Antiquarian Society and the American Genealogical Society, among others. He introduced the European concept and practice of folklife studies in the United States.
Scope and Content
Collection of field recordings made by professor Don Yoder to document various religious sects and religious and secular folk traditions primarily in Pennsylvania and in the northeastern United States. Included are recordings of Pennsylvania German conversation, interviews, hymns, prayers, church services including sermons, folk dance music, humorous songs, and folk festivals. Some tapes document Don Yoder's lectures and contain materials prepared for his classes on folk religion recorded by Dr. Yoder and other scholars and by his students at the University of Pennsylvania. Recordings were made of various events including the first Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic, August 30-September 1, 1961; and the second annual and other years of the Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival, Kutztown, Pennsylvania (recorded from a broadcast by WEEU) where participants were interviewed about local history; folk religious beliefs and practices, including prayer and the himmelsbrief; and healing traditions including Pennsylvania Dutch powwowing, and religious healing in Catholic and other traditions. Local choirs performed Pennsylvania German hymns and revival hymns, some in English; and Christmas music from Pennsylvania Dutch country. Other interviewees are a Russian woman who emigrated as a child and who speaks about Jewish customs related to pregnancy and birth; Italian Americans interviewed about miracles of healing, intercessory prayer, and the St. Anthony Beneficial Society, Glassboro, N.J.; Baptist church singers from Kentucky demonstrating lining-out hymnody; interviews about Shakers; and other unidentified content. Included is a sound tape reel of Korean shamanic chant. Manuscripts include a few published articles by Don Yoder and varied folk festival programs.
http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655344
Container List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Collection finding aid, 10 pp. (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Manuscript materials accompanying sound recordings (original), One linear inch. (Box-folder 1/2)
    Includes letters, documentation about the contents, specific sound recordings, and other related materials.
  - Audio containers, reels, and manuscript materials (photocopies), Folder 1 of 6, Includes documentation for SR001-035. (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Audio containers, reels, and manuscript materials (photocopies), Folder 2 of 6, Includes documentation for SR036-064. (Box-folder 1/4)
  - Audio containers, reels, and manuscript materials (photocopies), Folder 3 of 6, Includes documentation for SR065-088. No documentation for SR066, SR074-075, and SR089. (Box-folder 1/5)
  - Audio containers, reels, and manuscript materials (photocopies), Folder 4 of 6, Includes documentation for SR090-129. No documentation for SR115. (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Audio containers, reels, and manuscript materials (photocopies), Folder 5 of 6, Includes documentation for SR130-159. (Box-folder 1/7)
  - Audio containers, reels, and manuscript materials (photocopies), Folder 6 of 6, Includes documentation for SR160-170, plus a list of recordings made on October 9, 1968, at the home of Samuel H. Peachey. No documentation for SR171-174. (Box-folder 1/8)
  - Behney, William H. Choruses adapted to standard hymns: a collection for revival services, prayer meetings, etc. Lebanon Courier Print, ca. 1890s. 107 pages., 66 hymns, indexed by first lines. (Box-folder 1/9)
  - Publications by or about Don Yoder, Includes the program for the 1968 Smithsonian Institution Festival of American Folklife, Pennsylvania Folklife (Summer 1978), and Pennsylvania Heritage (Spring 2006). (Box-folder 1/10)
  - Original tape boxes for sound recordings, Includes containers for SR004, SR008, SR015, SR018, SR028, SR039, SR043, and SR050. (Box 2)
    Original boxes with information too faint to photocopy.
  - Original tape boxes for sound recordings, Includes containers for SR051, SR056, SR094, SR123-SR124, SR136, and SR148. (Box 3)
- Series II: Sound Recordings
  - Sound recordings, recorded ca.1951-1979, AFC 2003/051: SR001-SR174; 174 items, consisting of 152 sound tape reels, 21 sound cassettes, and 1 sound disc (45 rpm).
    Includes recordings of music and spoken word from the Pennsylvania Dutch Folk Festival (Kutztown, PA), the first Pennsylvania Dutch Harvest Frolic, and elsewhere; genres include spirituals, powwowing, dance music, and other styles. Sound quality various, especially since the majority of recordings were made outdoors. Also includes one sound tape reel of Korean shamanic chant.
- Series III: Graphic Materials
  - George Kaufmann, dulcimer builder and player, stringing his most recent board. Photo dated September 1968, AFC 2003/051: PH01; Black-and-white photographic print (3 1/2 x 5 in. ) (Box-folder 1/11)
  - A closer view of the "board." Photo dates from September 1968 (taken the same day as PH01), AFC 2003/051: PH02; Black-and-white photographic print (3 1/2 x 5 in. ) (Box-folder 1/12)